<tool id="ARGO_NAVIS" name="Introduction" version="1.0.0">
  <description>to Argo Navis</description>
  <help>


Argo Navis
----------


**Argo Navis** is a *set* of tools designed for carrying out *Ancestral Discrete Trait* analyses, for phylogeographics or molecular epidemiology.
It does this in a Bayesian setting, using BEAST to produce posteriors, and PACT as an analysis tool to extract information from these posteriors.


About discrete traits
---------------------

In general, a *discrete trait* is one which takes on some finite number of values.
In a phylogenetic setting, a discrete trait can represent geographical location, host species of a virus, or tissue compartment of a host.
We can model evolutionary histories in such a way that transitions in this discrete trait are accounted for.
This transitions might represent physical migration of organisms, or transmission of a virus from one host group to another.
Within this model we can think about the rate of transitions from one trait to another as the rate of migration from one location to another,
or the rate of zoonoses from one organism to another.


How Argo Navis is set up
------------------------

Argo Navis uses BEAST to perform it's phylogenetic and discrete trait analyses.
Setting up a configuration file to run with BEAST, and getting all of the settings just can be daunting for beginners.
For this reason, Argo Navis' BEAST tool automates as much of this work as possible, requiring you only to specify your sequence and discrete
trait data.
It also provides a number of powerful options for dealing with some of the finer points of settings up more custom analyses, all
of which can be configured through dropdown menus and text fields.

The second component of Argo Navis is PACT (Posterior Analysis of Coalescent Trees), developed by Trevor Bedford.
PACT takes the labeled trees output file from BEAST, and performs highly customizable and flexible analyses from it.
However, PACT is perhaps even more daunting to use than BEAST, as it's only configurable through text files which instruct PACT
as to the analyses it must perform.
But as with BEAST, Argo Navis wraps many of the features you'd most commonly want to use into a simple Graphical interface.

While Argo Navis can't expose all of the powerful features of both programs, it should help considerably with folks getting started doing
discrete state ancestral analyses.

For more help with the individual tools, including usage, and how to interpret the outputs, please see the documentation for each of
the two components.


Resources
---------

The following are some studies that have used some or all of these methods for discrete trait ancestral analysis:

* flu study
* astv study
* phylogeo examples?


Matsen FA IV, Small CT, Soliven K, Engel GA, Feeroz MM, et al. (2014) `A Novel Bayesian Method for Detection of APOBEC3-Mediated Hypermutation and Its Application to Zoonotic Transmission of Simian Foamy Viruses`_. PLoS Comput Biol 10(2): e1003493. doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003493

.. _wiki documentation: https://github.com/fhcrc/hyperfreq/wiki/Reference-sequence-strategies
.. _A Novel Bayesian Method for Detection of APOBEC3-Mediated Hypermutation and Its Application to Zoonotic Transmission of Simian Foamy Viruses: http://www.ploscompbiol.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003493

  </help>
</tool>
